Okay בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is מנחות כד, Menachos
chaf daled, מנחות Menachos 24.
We pick up on two lines from the bottom on כג עמוד
ב, chaf gimmel amud beis, the last word of the line, כי
סליק. ki salik. I should also say that it seems that yesterday's
recording half of it did not get recorded so we'll be updating
that recording momentarily. So check back for that. Anyway, we pick up
here two lines from the bottom כג עמוד ב chaf gimmel amud
beis and we just got through a whole major discussion about מנחות
menachos being mixed and issues about ביטול bittul
and מין במינו min bemino definitions according to רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
and now we actually turn on to a slightly different topic. כי
סליק רב כהנא, Ki salik Rav Kahana, when רב כהנא Rav Kahana
went up to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אשכחינהו לבני
רבי חייא, ashkecheinu livnei Rebbi Chiya, he found the children of the
sons of רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya דיתבי וקאמרי deyasvi vekaamri and they
were sitting and saying the following הלכה. halacha. עשרון שחלקו והניחו בביסא,
Isaron shecholko vehinicho bivisa, you have the עשרון isaron the flour being
used for a מנחה mincha and you divided it into two piles,
not touching, and you put them in some type of a vessel.
ונגע טבול יום באחד מהם מהו? Venaga tvul yom beechad meihen mahu?
And a טבול יום, tvul yom, somebody who went to the מקווה
mikvah that day and will be completely טהור tahor that night but
now because he's a טבול יום tvul yom his status is like
a שני לטומאה sheni letuma and therefore he has the ability to
make תרומה terumah טמא tamei and certainly something that is קודש kodesh
טמא. tamei.
So just trying to give an example of somebody with a very
minimal level of טומאה tumah but can still work in this case.
מהו? Mahu? What's the הלכה? halacha? Now what should the הלכה halacha
be? So the question is when he touches one pile does he
make the other pile טמא? tamei? Why should that be? You know
they're two separate objects, they're not touching. So because believe it or
not there's a הלכה halacha that when
קודש kodesh is in a vessel and we'll get to the parameters
of that it makes it as if it's all one object.
כדתנן, Kitnan, so then what's the question? Because we taught in the
משנה, mishna, כלי מצרף מה שבתוכו לקודש, kli metzaref mah shebesocho lekodesh,
and this is a משנה mishna in חגיגה Chagiga that items that
are all in the same vessel they're considered one item when you're
dealing with things that are קודש kodesh for the purposes of טומאה
וטהרה. tuma v'tahara. So what's the issue? Do we say הני מילי
היכא דנגעי בהדדי? hani mili heicha denagei bahadadei? Maybe that's only if
they're touching one another. אבל היכא דלא נגעי בהדדי לא? Aval heicha
delo nagei bahadadei lo?
But if they're not touching one another no? או דלמא לא שנא?
O dilma lo shana? Or maybe it doesn't make a difference? So
it's not totally clear if they're touching one another why you need
the כלי kli to be מצרף metzaref them at all, what would
be the חידוש? chiddush? But presumably you can still imagine two separate
piles that are touching but that they are shaped differently especially if
there's already oil mixed in with them let's say, so they're each
one has its own very distinct shape and they just happen to
touch so it's still not one unit. And if you were just
working with normal הלכות halachos of טומאה, tuma, the טבול יום tvul
yom would touch pile A and then pile A would have to
transfer the טומאה tuma to pile B, which it might not be
able to do. So do we when we say that it's that
everything in the vessel gets combined, is it only when those two
objects are touching one another or maybe it doesn't matter? Even if
they're separate, completely separate, since they're in the same vessel they're considered
for one when it comes to laws of טומאה tuma for something
that is קודש. kodesh. אמר להו, Amar lehu, so he רב כהנא
Rav Kahana said to the sons of רבי חייא: Rebbi Chiya: אמר
להו איהו, Amar lehu iyu, מי תנן כלי מחבר? mi tnan kli
mechaber? The משנה mishna doesn't say the vessel joins. כלי מצרף תנן.
Kli metzaref tnan. It says that it combines. So joins would mean
that they're already touching and it makes it one object. מצרף,
Metzaref, combines, is understood to mean that not as tight of a
unit, it doesn't make them into one unit but it does mean
that they're all connected and therefore for him that language indicates that
they're more separate and nevertheless the vessel connects them. כלי
מצרף, Kli metzaref, okay, so כל דהו, kol dehu, it means even
if they're in all circumstances even if it's a very minimal connection,
we're not trying to be מחבר mechaber them and make them one
unit, so therefore even if they're not touching the vessel combines them
all, connects them all. So yes it works across air space. If
you touch one and it's in the same vessel the other pile
becomes טמא. tamei. Okay so now we're going to ask questions building
on this. הושיט אחד ביניהן מהו? Hoshit echad bevineihen mahu? So let's
say you put another half of an עשרון isaron between these two
half עשרונות isronos and that half עשרון isaron doesn't belong because you
only have one. עשרון isaron for the מנחה. mincha. So there's something
extraneous here. So then what's the story? אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so he said back to them, so צריך לכלי
כלי מצרפו אין צריך לכלי אין כלי מצרפו. Tzarich likli kli metzarfo,
ein tzarich likli ein kli metzarfo. Something that is needed for the
vessel, the one עשרון isaron needs a כלי שרת kli shares to
make it into a מנחה, mincha, okay? And that so that becomes
is so therefore that's seen as one unit, whereas whereas an extra
עשרון isaron is not, you know, doesn't is not connected at all
to the vessel and therefore the vessel does not combine them. Okay.
הושיט טבול
יום את אצבעו ביניהם מהו? Hoshit tvul yom et etzba'o beineihem mahu?
Now let's say the טבול יום tvul yom didn't actually touch one
pile, but he just stuck his finger into the air space, maybe
into the space between pile A and pile B, because maybe the
imagine we're imagining that if it's combining pile A and pile B,
that therefore it is what do you call it? Then therefore, you
know, it's like the whole thing is filled with this with מנחה
mincha and therefore even touching the air space should transfer to the
whole thing. Everything is one unit, even the air. So he said
back,
אמר להו אין לך דבר שמטמא מאויר אלא כלי חרס בלבד. Amar
lehu ein lacha davar shemitamei me'avir ela kli cheres bilvad. No no
no, that is not what the הלכה halacha is. The only way
טומאה tumah transfers in the air space of a כלי kli is
if it is a כלי חרס, kli cheres, okay? The כלי, kli,
it's not a הלכה halacha that the כלי kli you know brings
the טומאה tumah throughout its air space. That's only something with a
כלי חרס. kli cheres. Here the הלכה halacha is things that are
the that need the כלי שרת kli shares and that are appropriate
for the כלי שרת, kli shares, if they're in if they're all
in it, they're considered connected for laws of טומאה טהרה. tumah tahara.
So if you touch one, they all become טמא. tamei. But if
you only touch the air space, then obviously, you know, you're not
transferring any טומאה. tumah. טומאה Tumah still transfers through direct touch. This
just combines all the things just to to bring the טומאה tumah
to all the items. Okay, but it's only the items that are
needed for the כלי, kli, you know, or that are appropriate for
the כלי kli and not something extraneous.
Okay, so now we continue. הדר איהו בעי מינייהו, Hadar ihu ba'ei
mineihu, so then, you know, Rav Kahana turned around and he asked
they were asking him questions, now he's asking them questions, the בני
רבי חייא. Bnei Rabbi Chiya. מהו
לקמוץ מזה על זה צירוף דאורייתא או דרבנן? Mahu likmotz mizeh al
zeh tziruf de'oraita o derabbanan? Can you take so you have these
two halves in this כלי שרת, kli shares, two halves of an
עשרון isaron and you made it into a מנחה. mincha. Can you
go ahead and take a קמיצה kmitza from one of the piles
and that will be a valid קמיצה kmitza on the whole מנחה?
mincha? What's the issue? Do we say צירוף דאורייתא או דרבנן? tziruf
de'oraita o derabbanan? Is this הלכה halacha that everything in the vessel
that is sort of you know that needs this vessel and is
like one קרבן korban as it were, one item, that they're combined
as one thing, is that a דאורייתא de'oraita הלכה? halacha? Where would
it be a דאורייתא? de'oraita? It's based on the פסוק pasuk of
כף אחת עשרה זהב, kaf achat asara zahav,
so כף אחת, kaf achat, everything in the כף kaf is considered
as one. Is that a real דאורייתא de'oraita principle? And then it's
okay, you have one מנחה, mincha, it's like all of the all
of the flour combined and you take your קמיצה kmitza and it's
good. Or is it only a דרבנן derabbanan principle and it's only
a חומרה chumra for טומאה tumah that we combine them and we
say the טומאה tumah transfers from one to the other, but דאורייתא
de'oraita it's really not the same and it really doesn't count as
one מנחה mincha if they're separate units, even if they're in the
same vessel?
So let's take a look.
אמרו ליה, Amru leh, so they said to him, זו לא שמענו.
zu lo shamanu. We did not hear a direct answer to this.
כי יוצא בו שמענו, Ki yotzei bo shamanu, but we heard something
in a similar discussion elsewhere that we think we can bring to
bear on this question. Okay, what did we hear? דתנן, Detnan, the
משנה Mishna teaches: שתי מנחות שלא נקמצו ונתערבו. Shtei menachot shelo nikmetzu
venitarvu. So this is our משנה, Mishna, this is why we're discussing
it here. You have two מנחות menachot that have don't have the
קמיצה kmitza taken from them, you have, you know, A and B
as we've discussed, okay? And they got mixed up, so now there's
an A-B overlap, but there's maybe still a separate A section and
a separate B section.
זו בזו, zo bezo, אם יכול לקמוץ מזו בפני עצמה ומזו בפני
עצמה, im yachol likmotz mizo bifnei atzma umizo bifnei atzma, if you
can take you know the קמיצה kmitza from A by itself, the
non-overlap part, and B by itself, the non-overlap part, then כשירות, ksherot,
then they're both kosher because each מנחה mincha had a pure קמיצה,
kmitza, a pure A taken and a pure B taken as the
קומץ. kometz. ואם לאו פסולות, Ve'im lav psulot, but if you need
the extra flour that's in the overlap part then you're stuck because
you can't take a pure A קמיצה kmitza with sufficient you know
stuff from just A and you can't take a pure B קמיצה.
kmitza. So now so how's that relevant? כי יכול לקמוץ מכשירה, ki
yachol likmotz mikshara, but if you can take the separate קמיצה kmitzah
of A and B, it's כשר. kasher. Okay, אמאי? amai? Now why
is it true? הך דמערב הלא נגע. hach d'ma'arev halo naga. The
stuff that is mixed together isn't touching. So because the גמרא Gemara
assumes that when it says how do you have an A and
a B and an AB, it assumes that what it means is
some of A separated from A and some of B separated from
B and you have a mixed pile. Okay, but they're not touching.
And that's how you can have A, AB and B, that each
one is a separate pile. So if that's true, you can take
the קמיצה kmitzah from A and it combines with the flour that's
in the AB pile. So that shows you we have to assume
it's in the same כלי שרת. kli shares. Okay, but that shows
you that you are that the כלי שרת kli shares makes it
all one even for making the קומץ kometz valid and the מנחה
mincha valid and therefore it's a דאורייתא de'oraita principle. So אמאי הך
דמערב הלא נגע? amai hach d'ma'arev halo naga? So אמר רבא, amar
Rava, so now רבא Rava who wasn't part of the conversation but
he responds back: I don't buy this proof.
דילמא בגושים המחולקים העשויים כמסרק. dilma begushim hamachulakim asuyim kemasreik. How do
you know? Maybe it's not that there's three separate piles. It's like
three separate pieces but all one pile, like a comb. What's a
comb? If you think about a comb, a comb has all these
separate teeth, but it's got the base of the comb that everything
is combined. So the base of the comb is the AB overlap
and the separate teeth are the separate, you know, one is an
A and one is a B. So we could be talking about
that everything is touching, but there's parts that are pure A and
pure B and then part of an overlap. We're not talking necessarily
about separate piles. Okay, so then we still don't have an answer.
So מאי הוה עלה? mai hava alah? What was the upshot? Is
this principle of צירוף כלי tziruf kli דאורייתא de'oraita that works even
to כשר kasher the מנחה, mincha, make it all one? Or is
it only דרבנן derabbanan for טומאה? tumah? So אמר רבא, amar Rava,
so said רבא Rava who raised the challenge before: תא שמע, tashma,
come and hear.
דתניא: detanya: והרים ממנו. v'herim mimenu. This is by the פסוק pasuk
by the קומץ: kometz: You shall take from it בקומצו b'kumtzo with
his, you know, handbreadth. ממנו מן המחובר. mimenu min hamachubar. Everything has
to be connected. All the מנחה mincha because right before, you know,
we've been discussing whether צירוף כלי tziruf kli works, but whoever said
the הלכה halacha that the מנחה mincha all has to be connected
as one unit? Whoever said I can't have half here and half
there and still, you know, maybe they were sanctified initially in one
כלי, kli, but maybe I can take the קמיצה kmitzah when they're
divided? So no, from this ממנו, mimenu, from it, we learn מן
המחובר. min hamachubar. It has to be one unit when you're taking
from it. שלא יביא עשרון בשני כלים ויקמוץ. shelo yavi isaron bishnei
kelim v'yikmotz. Don't take the divided into two separate vessels and take
קמיצה kmitzah from one vessel, that won't work. The מנחה mincha has
to be one unit. So he makes the very reasonable inference: הא
בכלי אחד דומיא דשני כלים, ha bikli echad dumya d'shnei kelim, if
it were in one vessel, even if it were somewhat similar to
two vessels, they were two separate piles in one vessel, it sounds
like קומץ, kometz, you could take the קמיצה. kmitzah. That's a pretty
good proof. It says it has to be one and what it
rules out is separate vessels. So it sounds like as long as
it's all in one vessel, even if it were separate piles, it
would be okay. אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye
said back to this:
דילמא שני כלים היכי דמי כגון קפיזא בקבא. dilma shnei kelim heichi
dami kagon kviza b'kava. No, maybe the two vessels that's no good
is sort of like a one type of a measuring vessel that's
carved out within another one. What does that mean? דאף על גב
דאריבי מעילאי כיון דמפסקי מחיצה דקפיזא מתתאי... de'af al gav d'arivi mei'ilai
keivan d'mifseki mechitza dekviza mitataei...
so that is... מתתאי, mitataei, it is a problem. לא, lo, it's
not good. Some add the word לא. lo. So, so the way
רש״י Rashi explains what this means, they clearly knew what type of
a vessel they were talking about when I'm thinking about this, I
think sort of about like those types of, you know, things that
they have trays that they have for kids that have like different
compartments in each one. So they're imagining that you've got a vessel
that's got these different
compartments and, and the wall dividing the compartment goes all the way
up to the height of the vessel. All right. So therefore, in
that case, that constitutes שני כלים shnei kelim and רש״י Rashi says
and it also could be a scenario where maybe the stuff touches,
you know, because it fills up each compartment, so they touch above
the wall dividing the compartments, but that is already outside of the
walls of the vessel. Okay, so let's read that again. So he
says like that: דאף על גב דאריבי מעילאי de'af al gav de'arivi
mei'ilai even though they are mixed on top. mixed above, okay, these
things the compartments are filled and the two halves of the מנחה
mincha touch each other after they fill up the compartments, okay, but
that's above the, you know, edge of the vessel, above the height
of the vessel. כיון דמפסיק מחיצה דכפיזא מתתאי keivan demfasiq mechitzah dekhfiza
mitattai since the wall of the compartment still divides all below for
the whole length of the vessel, that's not good. That's the case
that isn't good. And what is the case that is good? הכלי
אחד דומיא דבי כליים ha-kli echad dumya de-vei kilayim if it was
one vessel similar to two, היכי דמי heichi dami what's that like?
כגון עריבתא של תרנגולים kegon arivata shel tarnegolim like a, you know,
trough for chickens, obviously they knew the vessels that they were talking
about. And apparently the trough of chickens, the dividing wall between the
compartments ends before the top of the vessel.
ואף על גב דמפסיק מחיצה ve'af al gav demfasiq mechitzah and even
though the wall divides it, the wall of the compartments, הנגי, hanegei,
and
the two halves of the עשרון isaron in the separate compartments touch
one another within the walls of the vessel and that makes it
okay. So a very difficult read but basically what he is saying
is when the ברייתא braita implies that that in one vessel it's
always going to be okay, maybe it doesn't mean it. Maybe it
really means that in one vessel it'll be okay even if they're
separate at the bottom as long as they're connected above. That's what
it means that they'd be okay in one vessel, but fully separate
we're not talking about a scenario whether we're talking two vessels or
one vessel. We're not talking about a fully about fully separate. The
scenario we were talking about was when they were touching and the
only question is are they touching above the height of the vessel
or are they touching within the vessel itself?
Okay, so היכא דלא נגעי כלל תיבעי לך heicha dela nagei klal
tiba'ei lach you still have that question. So it did seem like
a very good proof but אביי Abaye said maybe we're talking about
some special scenario. All right, now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
בעי
רמי בר ירמיה, ba'ei Rami bar Yirmiyah, רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah asked.
We're not done yet with the צירוף כלי. tzeruf kli. ורבי ירמיה
ve-Rabbi Yirmiyah loves asking like, you know, like interesting thought
experiments about like particular like more strange scenarios. So רבי ירמיה Rabbi
Yirmiyah asked the following thing: צירוף כלי וחיבור מים מהו. tzeruf kli
ve-chibur mayim mahu. Let's say you have the idea of these two
halves of an עשרון isaron in one vessel, טמא tamei touches one,
the other one becomes טמא, tamei, okay, but you also have a
connection by water. So the way רש''י Rashi explains it is you
have these two halves, you have A and B pile in the
in the vessel, and then outside of the vessel you have C
and a pile of, you know, I don't know, a flour C,
and B and C are connected through a flowing of water. Imagine
or I don't know, imagine let's say some of the oil from
B is flowing out and it's running and it's touching C, okay?
And that normally would be considered or might be considered to make
them one. But the question is when A and B become one
to be combined, does that also mean that now that B is
going to become טמא tamei because the vessel's combining it, that טומאה
tumah will now also include C if B and C are only
connected through water?
So let's take a look. מי
תנן כלי מצרף מה שבתוכו לקודש, mi tnan kli mtzaref mah shebetokho
lekodesh, when we say that the vessel combines the things that are
in it for if they're הקדש, hekdesh, הני מילי דגואי, hanei milei
degavai, that's only things on the inside of the vessel, אבל דבראי
לא, aval debarai lo, but on the outside of the vessel no.
או דלמא כיון דמחבר מחבר, o dilma keivan demchaber mchaber, or do
we say no, since there's water connecting B and C, we consider
C gets שלעפט shlept along as well and it also C also
becomes טמא. tamei. Now I should say that תוספות Tosafot really struggles
with this גמרא Gemara because since when should a connection of liquid
between B and C work for טומאה? tumah? Like the it sounds
like the גמרא's Gemara assuming like that naturally would combine B and
C and we want to know if it just works in this
scenario with צירוף כלי. tzeruf kli. But why? Why? Since when does
liquid combine two separate foods and solids for purposes of טומאה? tumah?
So תוספות Tosafot tries to figure that out but we'll just sort
of leave it as it is. Okay, so now he goes on.
ואם תמצא לומר כיון דמחבר מחבר, ve'im timtza lomar keivan demchaber mchaber,
if we say since B and C are connected by water then
they're connected then that pulls C along and if you're מטמא metamei
A, it causes טומאה tumah to both B and
C, חיבור מים וצירוף כלי ונגע טבול יום מבחוץ מהו. chibur mayim
ve-tzeruf kli ve-naga tvul yom mibachutz mahu. What about if you did
it in the opposite direction? So you touched a טבול יום tvul
yom touched C. Because it's connected by liquid to B, that makes
B טמא. tamei. And now because B and A are in the
same vessel, will that have the ability to also transfer the טומאה
tumah to A? So that maybe is weaker. In the first case
you started that the טומאה tumah started with A, it because of
the principle of צירוף כלי tziruf kli worked and it transferred it
to B, and now maybe B and C are combined. But you
already had the principle of צירוף כלי tziruf kli working, bringing it
from A to B. Here you started with C, you got B
טמא. tamei. Since B did not come טמא tamei directly by טומאה
tumah occurring within the vessel, maybe there's no principle to say צירוף
כלי tziruf kli here. So what's the, what's the story? כי תנן
כלי מצרף הני מילי דנגע מגואי. Ki tnan kli mtzaref hani mili
dinaga migavai. Do you say when does the vessel combine, if you
touched in the vessel? You put your hand in the vessel and
you touched A, then it jumps to B, or you touch B,
it jumps to A. אבל מבראי לא, Aval mibarai lo, but if
you touch something outside of the vessel, C, then even if that
makes B טמא, tamei, the, the becoming, the original טומאה tumah occurred
outside the vessel, so that won't transfer to A. או דילמא לא
שנא, O dilma lo shna, maybe it doesn't matter? תיקו. Teiku. So
the גמרא Gemara does not answer that question. Okay, but again, it
is difficult the assumption that liquid can, would combine them, you know,
סתם ככה stam kacha as a general rule, and the only question
is the application to this case of צירוף כלי. tziruf kli. Anyway,
those are some questions about צירוף כלי tziruf kli and we also
don't have answered the principle about the question of whether it's still
right or not, would it work to make it all one for
the קמיצה kemitza of a מנחה, mincha, even though the simple sense
of the ברייתא braita quoted is that it was, the גמרא Gemara
said that was not definitive. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. בעא רבא, Bayei Rava, רבא Rava asked. עישרון שחלקו ונטמא
אחד מהן והניח בביסא וחזר טבול יום ונגע באותו טמא מהו. Isaron
shechilko venitma echad mehen vehiniach bebisah vechozar Tevul Yom venaga be-oso tamei
mahu. So you tell the גמרא Gemara really enjoys doing thought experiments
here. Okay, so he says you have an עישרון, isaron, and you
divided it up into two piles, A and B.
Not in a vessel. And you made pile A טמא. tamei. Some,
okay, not a טבול יום, Tevul Yom, some, I don't know, a
זב zav touched pile A. And now it's a ראשון לטומאה. rishon
l'tumah. And now you take that pile A and you put it
in a כלי, kli, in a vessel. וחזר טבול יום ונגע
באותו טמא מהו. Vechozar Tevul Yom venaga be-oso tamei mahu. And you
take, actually you take both piles, okay? So you now take A
and B. B is totally טהור. tahor. When A become, became טמא,
tamei, when the זב zav touched it and it became a ראשון
לטומאה, rishon l'tumah, they were, it was separate from B and they
were, and they were not in a כלי, kli, so no טומאה
tumah transferred. Then you went ahead and you put A and B
in the same vessel. And the assumption is that if A is
already טמא tamei it doesn't transfer to B. It's only when they're
in the vessel and then A becomes טמא tamei then it will
transfer to B. So you put A and B in the same
vessel. A remains a ראשון, rishon, B is totally טהור. tahor. וחזר
טבול יום ונגע באותו טמא מהו. Vechozar Tevul Yom venaga be-oso tamei
mahu. And then a טבול יום Tevul Yom comes and he touches
A. Okay? So now the טומאה tumah occurred in the vessel and
A should transfer to B. The only question is, is there any,
is there any significance of touching something that is already טמא tamei
and, and which would transfer a טומאה tumah that is of a
lighter טומאה? tumah? Okay? So it's already a ראשון rishon because it
was touched by a זב. zav. A טבול יום Tevul Yom is
going to touch it, that'll make it a שלישי, shlishi, a very
low level of טומאה. tumah. So do we consider it like, no,
he gave it a שלישי shlishi even though it was already a
ראשון, rishon, and that then transfers to B because now טומאה tumah
occurred within the vessel? Or do we say the act of touching
it when it was a ראשון rishon makes the touching of it
by a טבול יום Tevul Yom completely meaningless? מי אמרינן, Mi amrinan,
do we say שבעא ליה טומאה? sava lei tumah? That A is
already sated with טומאה? tumah? It's already טמא tamei at a high
level. It doesn't get an additional weak level of טומאה. tumah. או
לא? O lo? Or do we not say that? We say it's
a ראשון rishon and a שלישי, shlishi, it became a שלישי shlishi
and it transferred it now to the other pile. So אמר ליה
אביי, amar lei Abaye, that's a really nice question. So אביי Abaye
said to רבא, Rava, ומי אמרינן שבעא ליה טומאה? umi amrinan sava
lei tumah? Do we really have this principle that when something is
טמא tamei it's sated and then it can't get another level, a
weaker level of טומאה? tumah? והתנן, Ve-tnan, we taught in a משנה
Mishna in כלים. Kelim. סדין טמא מדרס. Sadin tamei midras. You have
a, you know, a sheet and it is טמא מדרס. tamei midras.
טמא מדרס tamei midras is the idea that if a זב zav
or a זבה zava sits on a seat even doesn't touch it,
even if there's ten cushions, the seat is considered to be, you
know, כל המשכב אשר ישכב עליו הזב יטמא וכל המרכב אשר ירכב
עליו הזב יטמא, kol hamishkav asher yishkav alav hazav yitma vechol hamerkav
asher yirkav alav hazav yitma, those explicit פסוקים pesukim in the תורה,
Torah, that because it's a משכב mishkav or a מושב moshav of
a זב zav or a זבה, zava, that's called מדרס, midras, literally
means like trampling, but something that's used for sitting on, that it
becomes an אב הטומאה av hatumah and even if the זב zav
doesn't touch it directly. So you have this sheet that was sat
on by a זב, zav, and it is an אב הטומאה. av
hatumah.
Okay? And you went ועשאו וילון, ve-asao vilon, and you went and
you said I'm not going to use this as a bedsheet anymore.
For I'm going to hang this up as a divider between as
a between two rooms.
So מהו? mahu? איתרמי מן המדרס, itrami min hamidras, so it stops
being this is fascinating without going to a מקווה mikvah because functionally
it is no longer a seat, it is no longer functioning as
something to sit on, it can't have the טומאה tumah of a
מדרס. midras. The טומאה tumah of a מדרס midras requires even if
it already got that טומאה, tumah, that טומאה tumah will only continue
as long as it's still considered to be a type of a
seat, something you sit on or lie on. Now that it is
a curtain, it loses the טומאה tumah of the מדרס. midras. But
nevertheless אבל טמא מגע מדרס. aval tamei maga midras. It has the
טומאה tumah of something that touched a מדרס. midras. So this is
a very it's a strange idea which is okay the טומאה tumah
of the אב הטומאה av hatumah goes off, but the sheet remains
a ראשון. rishon. Why? Because it touched a מדרס. midras. What מדרס
midras did it touch? It touched itself. Okay? So while it was
a מדרס midras it was also touching itself, which is a strange
idea, and therefore even when it stops being a מדרס midras it
still has the and it stops being an אב, av, this has
the status of something that touched מדרס midras and it's a ראשון.
rishon. אמר רבי יוסי. amar Rabbi Yosi. So Rabbi Yosi argues on
this in the משנה. mishnah. וכי באיזה מדרס נגע זה? v'chi b'eizeh
midras naga zeh?
This sheet never touched a מדרס. midras. It was a מדרס, midras,
it never touched a
מדרס. midras. אלא אלא שנגע בו הזב טמא מגע הזב. ela ela
shenaga bo hazav tamei maga hazav. Okay, but what I will concede
is if the זב zav actually touched it, okay, then it will
have the טומאה tumah of being touched by a זב. zav. So
it doesn't magically become considered something that touched a מדרס. midras. And
if this was a מדרס midras never touched by a זב, zav,
let's say I don't know it was a bottom cushion and the
זב zav sat on a top cushion, then it was never it
never touched a מדרס midras and it never touched a זב zav
and it's totally טהור tahor now that you made it into a
curtain. But if a זב zav touched it, then even when it
stops being a מדרס, midras, it will still have the טומאה tumah
of a ראשון rishon because it was touched by a זב. zav.
All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says, all right, that's the
משנה. mishnah. So we're not going to pay attention to this idea
of מגע מדרס maga midras because that's a strange idea and maybe
that's unique and not transferable to our case. But we are going
to look at Rabbi Yosi who speaks about a זב zav touching
something that presumably was already a מדרס. midras. So the גמרא Gemara
says so he's the גמרא Gemara says כי נגע בו הזב. ki
naga bo hazav. But
so okay, but in Rabbi Yosi's case when a זב zav did
touch it, מי איתמי? mi itamei? It is טמא. tamei. And presumably
even when it stops being a מדרס. midras. And presumably that's a
case ואפילו לבסוף v'afilu l'vasof even
even if the זב zav touched it after it was a מדרס.
midras. Now Rabbi Yosi didn't say that, but since he didn't qualify,
we're assuming Rabbi Yosi would include a case that first it was
a מדרס midras and it was and it was an אב av
and then a זב zav touched it and it was already an
אב av and a זב zav touching something can only make it
a ראשון rishon and nevertheless it got that additional ראשון rishon status
and now when the אב av status disappears because it was made
into a curtain, the ראשון rishon status still remains. So if that
was the sequence, it's a very good proof to our case that
you can add a weaker level of טומאה tumah even when something
has a higher level. So the גמרא Gemara so it's the גמרא
Gemara says so that's the case. אמאי? amai? Why does that weaker
level remain? לימא סבר לה טומאה? leima savar lah tumah? Why not
say according to you that it was sated with טומאה? tumah? We
don't say that. We see from Rabbi Yosi that it can become
a ראשון rishon even though it's already an אב. av. So אמר
ליה. amar leh. So Rava said back, ומי מייתי דהאי שנגע בו
הזב לבתר מדרס? u'mi mayiti d'hai shenaga bo hazav l'vatar midras? What
makes you assume that Rabbi Yosi's scenario is that the זב zav
touched after it became a מדרס? midras? If that were the case,
you'd be totally right. That would prove that even if something is
an אב, av, it can also be a ראשון. rishon. Something can
get a lower level of טומאה tumah even if it's a higher
level. דילמא מקמי מדרס? dilma mikamei midras? Maybe maybe Rabbi Yosi was
talking about the reverse order. First a זב zav touched and then
the זב zav sat on it. So first it was a ראשון
rishon and then it was an אב. av. And then that case
it has both levels and when the אב av goes away the
ראשון rishon remains because the ראשון rishon got there first, but it
would not become a ראשון rishon once it was already an אב.
av. דהוי טומאה חמורה על טומאה קלה. d'havei tumah chamurah al tumah
kalah. So the זב zav first touched it, so then the weightier
טומאה tumah came after the lighter one. That can happen and it
can have both levels. אבל הכא דאידי ואידי טומאה קלה לא. aval
hacha d'eidi v'eidi tumah kalah lo. But in our case where they're
both a light טומאה tumah or
maybe equal level or certainly in a case when it's a weightier
one followed by a light one, then you could say there's no
point in adding a layer if it's already at a higher level.
All right, so nice try, but we don't know the sequence of
Rabbi Yosi. So it's not clear whether we say this idea of
סבר לה טומאה savar lah tumah or not.
אלא מסיפא. ela miseyfa. Okay fine, let's try to prove it from
the end of that
משנה. mishnah. מודה רבי יוסי. modeh Rabbi Yosi. רבי יוסי Rebi Yosi
would concede if you had two blankets that were folded up and
put on one top of the other, bottom and a top. וישב
זב עליה Veyashav zav aleha and a זב zav sat on the
top, on the top. So the זב's zav body only touched the
top one, but both of them are מדרס midras because both of
them are cushions for a זב. zav. But his body only touched
the top one. שהעליון טמא מדרס והתחתון טמא מדרס ומגע מדרס. Sheha'elyon
tameh midras vehataxton tameh midras umaga midras. Okay, that the top one
actually is the top one the זב zav sat is a מדרס
midras because it was touched by because it was both of them
are מדרס midras because both of them were cushions of the זב.
zav. But the bottom one also was something that was touched by
a מדרס. midras. Okay, if you say it's A and B, A
is the top, B is the bottom. A and B are both
cushions for the זב, zav, so they're both a מדרס. midras. But
B was touched by A. So B also has the טומאה tumah
of מגע מדרס. maga midras. And in that case, if you make
them into curtains, A stops being a מדרס, midras, it then becomes
totally טהור, tahor, but B stops being a מדרס midras but it
will retain the טומאה tumah of מגע מדרס maga midras because it
touched A.
All right, so now the גמרא gemara says ואמאי ve'amai now why
did B get the טומאה tumah of מגע מדרס maga midras of
touching a מדרס? midras? לימא סבלי טומאה leima savlei tumah because B
was a full מדרס, midras, it was an אב, av, so why
does it also get the טומאה tumah of touching the מדרס midras
of touching A? Why don't we say it already has a higher
level, it can't get the lower level? So the answer here is
very obvious. So the גמרא gemara says no, התם בבת אחת הכא
בזה אחר זה. Hatam bevas achas hacha bezeh achar zeh. That was
at the same time, at the same moment that it became a
מדרס, midras, it became a מגע מדרס. maga midras. Both were happening
exactly at the same moment. So we're okay with something having multiple
levels of טומאה tumah and it can have a weak one followed
by a heavy one. It can even have a weak and a
heavy come at the same time. But what we're saying is once
it has the heavy level, there would not be a weak level
that would be layered on top of it, or at least that's
the question that we're asking. Okay, so we do not know the
answer to that. Very interesting conceptual question. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, another
question about this whole you know you can tell like I said
the גמרא's gemara having fun with these ideas of the כלי kli
being מצריף matzrif the two halves of the עישרון. issaron. עישרון שחלקה,
Issaron shechalko, you and this is going to sort of sound a
little bit like a like a Heidegger's what is it Schrödinger's cat.
You'll see what I mean. Schrödinger's מנחה. mincha. Okay, so עישרון שחלקה,
issaron shechalko, you divided the עישרון issaron into two halves A and
B. ואבד אחד מהן Ve'avad echad mehen
and you one half got lost, B got lost. והפריש אחר תחתיו
Vehifrish acher tachtav so then we went ahead and we separated out
another half an עישרון, issaron, we'll call it B-prime to now become
the מנחה mincha together with A. All right, ונמצא הראשון Venimtza harishon
and then you found B. So now you have A, B, and
B-prime. Okay,
ונמצא הראשון. Venimtza harishon. הרי שלושתן מונחים בביסא. Harei sheloshtan munachim bevisa.
Now they're all in one vessel and the vessel is מצריף. matzrif.
But what is it מצריף? matzrif? It's מצריף matzrif A to which
one, to B or B-prime? Either of those could be used for
the מנחה. mincha. You know you're going to have to choose whether
you want to use B or B-prime. So how does the צירוף
tziruf work in that case?
נטמא אבוד, Nitma avud, if the one that was lost, that's B,
becomes טמא, tameh, if somebody touched B, so אבוד וראשון מצטרפין. Avud
verishon mitztarfin. B and A combine because B if you're starting with
B then you know that B and A are connected because B
the only mate of B is going to be A, it won't
be B-prime.
מופרש אין מצטרף Mufrash ein mitztaref but B-prime doesn't get become טמא
tameh from B. There's no connection between B and B-prime. They're both
competing for A's affections as it were, but there's no connection between
the two of them. So B becoming טמא tameh will transfer to
A but not to
B-prime. נטמא מופרש, Nitma mufrash, if B-prime became טמא, tameh, מופרש וראשון
מצטרפין, Mufrash verishon mitztarfin, so B-prime and A, it transfers to A
because B-prime and A are potentially connected.
אבוד אין מצטרף Avud ein mitztaref but B doesn't become טמא tameh
because again B-prime and B have no points of no connection.
נטמא ראשון, Nitma rishon, if A became טמא, tameh, שניהם מצטרפין, Sheneihem
mitztarfin, so then A has connection to B and B-prime, either one
of those could be the second half. So therefore, if A becomes
טמא, tameh, both B and B-prime become טמא. tameh. אביי אמר, Abaye
amar,
now אביי Abaye says, אפילו נטמא אחד מהן נמי שניהם מצטרפין. Afilu
nitma echad mehen nami sheneihem mitztarfin. Even if any one of them
becomes טמא, tameh, even B becomes טמא tameh or B-prime becomes טמא,
tameh, everything becomes טמא. tameh. Why? There's no connection between between B
and B prime, מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why? כולהו בני בקתא דהדדי
נינהו, kulu bnei bikta dehadadi ninu, because they're all living in the
same household. Okay? They all are connected to one another, it's true
through A, not through one another, but nevertheless, they're in the same
vessel, so that essentially makes allows צירוף tzeruf to work even across
the lines that are not direct. Okay, מדמיתנא, medamtena, to give another
analogy, you have a household that has, you know,
some, you know, three siblings there. You know
A and B are half brothers from the mother and A and
C are half brothers from the father. Okay, so Abaye is saying,
so even though B and C are not related to each other
at all, they're only related through A, Abaye says yeah, but they're
all living in the same house. So anything that happens to one
happens to all three of them. Okay. וכן לענין קמיצה, vechen le'inyan
kemitzah, and a similar idea would happen by a קמיצה. kemitzah. קמץ
מן האבוד, kamatza min ha'avud,
שיירה וראשון נאכלים, shirayu verishon ne'echalin, מופרש אינו נאכל. mufrash eino ne'echal.
So if you take the קמיצה kemitzah from the one that got
lost, B, alright again they're in the same vessel because we just
we learned that the קמיצה kemitzah has to be all together when
it's in the same vessel. So you took the קמיצה kemitzah from
B,
then whatever's left of B after the קמיצה kemitzah and A can
be eaten, that defines the מנחה, minchah, B and A because you
took the קמיצה kemitzah from B. מופרש אינו נאכל, mufrash eino ne'echal,
but B prime can't be eaten because obviously B prime is not
the same מנחה minchah with B and A.
קמץ מן המופרש, kamatza min hamufrash, if you took the קמיצה kemitzah
from B prime, the one separated to replace it, שיירה וראשון נאכלים,
shirayu verishon ne'echalin, what's left of B prime and A can be
eaten because that means that the מנחה minchah is now defined as
being B prime and A.
אבוד אינו נאכל, avud eino ne'echal, but B can't be eaten because
B is not part of the מנחה minchah of B prime and
A. קמץ מן הראשון, kamatza min harishon, let's say you took the
קמיצה kemitzah from A, so שניהם אינם נאכלים, shneihem ainam ne'echalim, you
can't eat B or B prime. Why? Because the מנחה minchah can
only be an עשרון. isaron. So when you took it from A,
it's not defined whether B is part of the מנחה minchah or
B prime is part of the מנחה. minchah. And therefore because you
really don't know which one is the מנחה, minchah, right, then you
know the one that isn't the מנחה minchah is קודש kodesh but
can't be eaten, only the one that was part of the מנחה
minchah can now be eaten. So since you don't know how to
be able to determine which is which, okay, neither of them can
be eaten. ואביי אמר, ve'Abaye amar, and Abaye says the same thing,
אפילו קמץ מאחד מהם שניהם אינם נאכלים. afilu kamatz me'echad meihem shneihem
ainam ne'echalim. No, but here what Abaye is saying, well I guess
Abaye said before it was לחומרא lechumra and here it's also לחומרא,
lechumra, when he makes them all connected. Abaye says even when you
take from B or B prime you can't eat anything because why?
Even though there's no connection to B or B prime, why? מאי
טעמא, mai ta'ama, כולהו נמי בני בקתא דהדדי נינהו, kulu nami bnei
bikta dehadadi ninu, they're all part of the same household. Okay? Now
that's a bigger חידוש. chiddush. It's one thing to say like טומאה
tumah spreads throughout you know, but in this case you took from
B and we're going to say that nevertheless B prime cannot be
seen as not part of the same מנחה. minchah. Even though you
took from B and it's either B or B prime essentially they're
competing for which is part of the מנחה, minchah, so once you
take from B, B prime can't be part of it, since they
both are potentially connected to A and they're all in the same
כלי, kli, it's also seen as still part of the מנחה minchah
and therefore you have a מנחה minchah with two halves of which
they both, those two halves B and B prime have an indeterminate
status. Okay. בני בקתא דהדדי, bnei bikta dehadadi, רב פפא Rav Pappa
asked, ושיירים דידי מי נאכלים? ushiyarayim didi mi ne'echalim? In your scenario
of A and B and B prime, when you take the קומץ,
kometz, you're saying that B and B prime cannot be eaten because
it's indeterminate which one of those is connected to A, but the
remnant of A is definitely part of the מנחה minchah and it
can be eaten. So why is that? האיכא דנקא דקומץ דלא קריב?
ha'ika danka dekometz dela kariv? There is a sixth of the קומץ
kometz that can't be offered up. What does that mean? So what
it means is that because it's indeterminate between B and B prime,
the קומץ kometz is, is connected, is works for A and B
and B prime, right? For the מנחה minchah to be good it
has to sort of work for all of them because it has
to work for both B and B prime even though it's indeterminate
which one, which one it's working for. Okay, if that's true though,
the קומץ kometz is one third for A, this is the way
he imagines it, one third for A, one third for B, and
one third for B prime. However,
only B or B prime works.
So this קומץ kometz represents three halves, but but you know it's
got, there are thirds of it, each third of this קומץ kometz
represents a half, but only two of those thirds are working for
the two halves of the מנחה. minchah. The final third is opposite
the third, you know, half, which is not part of the מנחה.
mincha. So it should be considered that this קומץ kometz is only
two-thirds of a קומץ. kometz. Another way of saying that is if
the מנחה mincha now consists of three piles, A, B, and B
prime, because they're all part of the same מנחה mincha because B
and B prime with their indeterminate status, okay, then if the קומץ
kometz now represents three piles, but the קומץ kometz is only meant
for two piles, so it really is only two-thirds of a קומץ.
kometz. All right, so there's a sixth that is not offered. Now
what does it mean a sixth? It should really be a third.
But what it means is that a sixth of B and a
sixth from B prime, you know, you know, are, are not legitimately
taken care of.
So מתיב ליה רב פפא בריה דרב משרשיא, Matkiv lei Rav Papa
brei d'Rav Masharshiya, רב פפא בריה דרב משרשיא Rav Papa brei d'Rav
Masharshiya asked a similar question. קומץ גופיה היכי קרב? Kometz gufeh heichi
karev? It's not just how can you eat the שירים shirayim of
it? If you say how can you even offer up the קומץ?
kometz? האי איכא תילתא דחולין, Hai ika tilta d'chulin, one-third of it
is חולין. chulin. That's clear to refer to as a third, okay?
A third of it represents, you know, either B or B prime.
So ורב אשי אמר, Ve'Rav Ashi amar, now Rav Ashi doesn't think
those are questions. קומץ בדעתיה דכהנא תליא מילתא Kometz beda'ateih d'kahana talya
milta because כהן kohen כי קמץ עישרון קא קמץ. ki kamatz issaron
ka kamatz. The קומץ kometz is defined by the intent of the
כהן, kohen, and the כהן kohen only wants it to work for
an עישרון. issaron. It is true that objectively we can't identify the
second half of the עישרון, issaron, is it B or is it
B prime, okay? But nevertheless the כהן kohen isn't, you know, because
the כהן's kohen intent matters, he's intending that it works for whatever
the עישרון issaron is. We don't say it's working for the עישרון
issaron and a half. If we said it was working for the
עישרון issaron and a half, and only, and that extra half is
not a legitimate part of the מנחה, mincha, that would invalidate a
third of the קומץ. kometz. But the כהן kohen gets to say
that it is only working for one עישרון issaron here even if
it can't be determined what exactly that עישרון issaron is. Okay, so
that was very fun imagining that thing about operating between jumping over
air spaces and when you affect one half affecting the other and
the indeterminate status and we will end with this for today.